We were gone for eight months and in the meantime we started to get perspectives on things.
When you live outside your everyday life, these thoughts come.
We were in Mexico, where I have family and suddenly had more time for each other-
-More time for our children, and more time for friends and relatives.
We felt we wanted to get that feeling at home.
At home, it felt like a transport route for the weekend or for the holiday.
They worked to get these breaks.
We wanted to bring that feeling we had.
We didn't have the words for it then.
But now we call it an everyday life that we do not need to take vacation from.
We want the change where vacation is something different to everyday-
-But it should not be a quality difference.
Everyday life should be good, desirable.
It felt like Goldable.
Then it coincided with our experience in Mexico by a life-
-As we looked like we wanted life to look.
So it fit perfectly together.
I think it says: "Financial Freedom Through Badassity."
There was a lot of focus on thrift.
Cycle everywhere.
Do a lot of yourself.
We were attracted a lot of that.
Don't be so small.
There is a quote that inspired you some.
-Here we have it.
-"Common Sense is not very common."
It may not have inspired us so much, but that is something we have discovered.
It should be common sense not to waste money, nature's resources or their time.
Sometimes when we talk about what we have done, it feels like we just stumble up common sense.
But it is so natural for us to be so ineffective.
Here I also have you - where you pull in the same direction.
Why has it been important to you during the savings journey?
Yes, it is almost a necessity.
To talk together, to have common goals that you pull against together.
You know what happens if you sit in a canoe and paddle in different directions.
When we have common goals, we have been able to pepper each other.
When someone is not really motivated, you do not have a bad day at the same time.
Then we have been able to pepper each other because we are heading in the same direction.
It applies to both economic and all our lives that we try to choose the direction in the same direction.
And tune in this direction.
It can change.
When we arrived at it, we began to look at-
-What expenses that do not add to our quality of life.
In the short term, it was the simple things.
Actually what is always in the newspaper on January 24:
"Bring your lunch box, cycle instead of taking the car" ...
"Pull in everything everyday, don't buy more clothes if it's already full in the closet."
It was the first things.
We started to cooperate, started living more locally and seeing what we had around us.
In the next step it was to design for life.
Oskar likes to count, so he started counting on it.
We saw a pension around 55.
But it went a little faster.
When you started counting on it, what was the sum you got?
We started from the four percent rule.
I want to call it a rule of thumb.
If you think it is an absolute truth, it can be a little dangerous.
If you look at how we use it, then it is a feature of-
-How much you need to live and how much capital you have.
One of the reasons why this time became shorter was that we became more capable on-
-To put away money, but also live better on a smaller sum than we could dream of.
When we realized it, it became a smaller sum we needed to save.
This time shrunk.
Didn't you feel that you sacrificed anything or missed anything?
The cheeses maybe.
I am very fond of good cheeses.
But it was also like an experiment to see what you can do.
What do we want a lot?
What do we want in our lives?
How did investment go in the beginning?
We made a plan at the beginning of the year.
Around this much we can probably put away per month.
Then we bought shares for that amount every month, so it became an equally large buy-
-In the end of each month.
Wages and expenses went up and down-
-And it got a little over we saved it on a bank account
-So that for a period, for example, we could buy for 25,000 per month.
If the stock market went up it was fun and went down we got a little more for the money.
It didn't feel like we went in with a huge amount-
-So that it gets too hard to hold on if it goes down.
Have you been worried sometime during the savings trip?
No, rather the opposite.
The more we have saved, the safer we have felt.